Guide to the James Cecil Nelson Papers 1934-1975
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
- Series 3: Transport Economics Courses and Research Files, 1932-1974
  - Econ. 464: Land Transportation Agencies:
    - Regional Transportation: New England, 1945-1954; 20 items. (Box 13, Folder 201)
    - Transport Data and Statistics, Current Trends, 1966-1971; 30 items. (Box 13, Folder 202)
    - Transport Research Foundation, 1957-1966; 10 items. (Box 14, Folder 203)
    - Transport Technology - New Developments, Implications for Progress and Social Welfare, May 19 1975; 50 items. (Box 14, Folder 204)
    - Transport Theory Publications, 1958-1969; 20 items. (Box 14, Folder 205)
    - Transportation Association of America. Transportation Facts and Trends, 1964-1972; 9 items. (Box 14, Folder 206)
    - Transportation, Department of, 1966-1967; 70 items. (Box 14, Folder 207)
    - Transportation Events, 1965-1970; 60 items. (Box 14, Folder 208)
    - Transportation Policy Questions, 11 items. (Box 14, Folder 209)
    - Transportation Regulatory Modernization Act, 1972; 5 items. (Box 14, Folder 210)
    - Transportation Research: General Sources, 1957-1967; 25 items. (Box 14, Folder 211)
  - Econ. 465: Air and Water Transport:
    - Air Transport, 1950-1973; 40 items. (Box 14, Folder 212-213)
    - Civil Aeronautics Board Document Files, 1944-1971
      - Air Carriers
        - Foreign, Temporary. Cases, 1962; 4 (Box 14, Folder 214)
        - Large Irregular. Investigation, 1952-1965; 34 (Box 14, Folder 215-218)
        - Large Irregular, 1950-1954; 14 (Box 15, Folder 219)
        - Military Contract, 1962; 2 (Box 15, Folder 220)
        - Nonscheduled. Historical Files, 1948-1952; 70 (Box 15, Folder 221)
        - Supplemental, 1960-1968; 45 (Box 15, Folder 222-225)
      - Air Freight Cases, 1965; 3 items. (Box 15, Folder 226)
      - Air Freight, Domestic. Study Publication, 1957-1973; 15 items. (Box 15, Folder 227)
      - Air Service, Domestic. Cases, 1947-1962; 4 items. (Box 15, Folder 228)
      - Air Taxi Service, Regulations, 1970-1972 (Box 15, Folder 229)
      - Air Transport:
        - Connecticut General Public Symposium, Papers, 1961-1967; 20 (Box 15, Folder 230)
        - Federal Policy Reports, 1954-1961; 8 (Box 15, Folder 231)
        - Resource File, 1953-1954; 7 (Box 15, Folder 232)
        - Western Regional Reports, 1951-1970; 4 (Box 16, Folder 233)
      - Airlines:
        - Merger Cases, 1947-1964; 26 (Box 16, Folder 234-235)
        - Nonscheduled. Regulations and Cases, 1946-1955; 1966-1971; 130 (Box 16, Folder 236-237)
      - Airport and Air Service Study, Washington State, 1972; 25 items. (Box 16, Folder 238)
      - Alaskan Air Transport File, 1947-1949; 8 items. (Box 16, Folder 239)
      - Coach-type Service Case:
        - Interstate, 1949-1950; 11 (Box 16, Folder 240-241)
        - Transcontinental, 1949-1951; 13 (Box 16, Folder 242)
      - Enforcement Proceedings, 1958-1964; 8 items. (Box 16, Folder 243)
      - Hawaii Common Fares Case, 1950; 1962; 4 items. (Box 16, Folder 244)
      - Mail Payments to Domestic Air Carriers, Administrative Separation of Subsidy, 1952-1953; 4 items. (Box 16, Folder 245)
      - North Atlantic Charter Service, 1969; 5 items. (Box 16, Folder 246)
      - North Atlantic Route Case, 1945; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 247)
      - Northwest Airlines Domestic Operation, 1947 and 1952; 2 items. (Box 16, Folder 248)
      - Pacific Northwest-Southwest Service investigation, re-opened, 1964-1968; 7 items. (Box 17, Folder 249-250)
      - Passenger Fare Investigation:
        - Domestic, 1970-1972; 5 (Box 17, Folder 251-252)
        - General, 1953-1959; 11 (Box 17, Folder 253-255)
      - Quad-Cities Airport Historical File, 1971-1972; 75 items. (Box 17, Folder 256)
      - Regional Airports, New England Master Plan, Summary Report, 1961; 2 items. (Box 17, Folder 257)
      - Short Haul Coach Fare Investigation, 1953; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 258)
      - Southern Service to the West Case, 1951-1954; 9 items. (Box 17, Folder 259)
      - Southern Transcontinental Service Case, 1961; 2 items. (Box 18, Folder 260)
      - Transpacific Service Cases, 1946-1966; 15 items. (Box 18, Folder 261)
      - Twin Cities-Milwaukee Long Haul Investigation, 1969-1970; 6 items. (Box 18, Folder 262)
      - United States-Europe-Middle East Cargo Service Case, 1950; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 263)
      - West Coast File, 1944-1966; 40 items. (Box 18, Folder 264-265)
      - West Coast-Hawaii Service Cases, 1948; 1955; 2 items. (Box 18, Folder 266)
    - Federal Maritime Board Documents, 1941-1963; 145 items. (Box 18, Folder 267-269)
    - Water Transport (Ocean), Economics, 1964-1974; 65 items. (Box 18, Folder 270)
  - Econ. 468: Public Utility Economics:
    - California Public Utilities Documents, 1958; 3 items. (Box 19, Folder 271)
    - Federal Documents on Public Utilities, 1944; 1959; 3 items. (Box 19, Folder 272)
    - Federal Power Commission Documents, 1945-1955; 30 items. (Box 19, Folder 273-274)
    - Financial Problems of Public Utilities Seminar, 1959-1961; 22 items. (Box 19, Folder 275)
    - Public Utility Economics Seminar, 1962; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 276)
    - Public Utility Topics, 1958-1963; 2 items. (Box 19, Folder 277)
  - Econ. 564: Rail Management Seminar:
    - Material for Rail Management Seminar, 1963-1968; 30 items. (Box 19, Folder 278)
  - Graduate and Senior Level Economics Papers (no course association), 1953; 1964; 2 items. (Box 19, Folder 279)
- Series 4: Professional Activities, 1947-1975
  - Consultation and Testimony, 1951-1971
    - Alberta and Canada Freight Rates, 1960; 4 items. (Box 19, Folder 280)
    - Auto Manufacturers Association, Consultation, 1966; 3 items. (Box 19, Folder 281)
    - Canadian Transport Policy, 1960-1963; 40 items. (Box 19, Folder 282)
    - Economic Effects of Changes in Legal Vehicle Weights and Dimensions on Highways, NCHRP Project Proposal, 1970-1971; 9 items. (Box 19, Folder 283)
    - Highway Improvement, Report on Economic Impact of, 1959; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 284)
    - North Dakota Highway Finance Study, 1951; 5 items. (Box 19, Folder 285)
    - Rail Mergers:
      - B and O - C and O Case, 1960-1963; 20 items. (Box 19, Folder 286)
      - Documents:
        - Barringer, John W. Testimony, 1961; 3 (Box 19, Folder 287)
        - Crippen, C. E. Testimony, 1966; 5 (Box 19, Folder 288)
        - Interstate Commerce Commission Rail Merger Documents, 1956-1969; 45 (Box 20, Folder 289-293)
        - Supreme Court Briefs and Judgements, 1969-1970; 3 (Box 20, Folder 294)
      - Great Northern-Northern Pacific Case, 1965-1967; 25 items. (Box 20, Folder 295)
      - Norfold and Western-Nickle Plate-Wabash Case, 1962-1964; 25 items. (Box 20, Folder 296)
      - Publications, 1960-1967; 12 items. (Box 21, Folder 297-299)
      - Southern Clipping File, 1962-1965; 12 items. (Box 21, Folder 300)
    - Royal Commission on Transportation:
      - Long-Short Haul Discrimination, Alberta, 1958-1962; 22 items. (Box 21, Folder 301)
      - Submissions of Provinces, Reports on Freight Regulation Effects, 1960; 8 items. (Box 21, Folder 302-303)
      - Submissions of Provinces, 1949; 2 items. (Box 21, Folder 304)
      - Testimony, James C. Nelson, 1960; 25 items. (Box 21, Folder 305)
    - Senate Select Committee on Small Business, Testimony, 1955; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 306)
    - Statement by J. C. Nelson before the Interstate Commerce Commission, 1970; 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 307)
    - Transportation Improvements in Underdeveloped Countries, Publications, 1952-1971; 10 items. (Box 21, Folder 308)
    - Utah Study in Western Pacific Case, 1961; 8 items. (Box 21, Folder 309)
    - Volume Rates, Agreed Rates, 1956-1959; 20 items. (Box 21, Folder 310)
    - Western Pacific Acquisition of Control Case, 1961-1965; 30 items. (Box 21, Folder 311)
  - Publications, 1947-1975
    - Conferences
      - American Economic Association, Boston Transportation and Research Forum, December 1964.; 55 items. (Box 21, Folder 312)
      - Association of Oil Pipe Lines, Educator's Tour, June 18-24, 1960; 15 items. (Box 21, Folder 313)
      - Committee for Economic Development Transit Policy Discussion, Developing Metropolitan Transportation Policies, May 1965; 15 items. (Box 21, Folder 314)
      - Forum on Optimizing Transport Potential, September 1966; 15 items. (Box 22, Folder 315)
      - Industrial and Economic Development Conference, 5th Annual, Transportation, Walla Walla, WA, October 3-4, 1963; 15 items. (Box 22, Folder 316)
      - Washington State University, Wheat Marketing in the Northwest, 2nd Annual Workshop, January 1963; 25 items. (Box 22, Folder 317)
    - Papers and Publications Reviewed by Nelson
      - Dearing, Charles L. Transportation and Communications. Chapter XVI of Government Expenditures Study, 1956; 2 items. (Box 22, Folder 318)
      - Papers reviewed by Nelson, undated; 3 items. (Box 22, Folder 319)
      - Pendleton, William C. Economic Impact of Highway Improvement, 1958; 45 items. (Box 22, Folder 320-321)
      - SARC, Cost Based Freight Rates Study, 1966-1967; 1 item. (Box 22, Folder 322)
    - Papers Presented by Nelson
      - The Challenge of Transportation, Washington State University Invited Address, 1966; 45 items. (Box 23, Folder 323)
      - Conference Papers Presented by Nelson, 1941-1973; 50 items. (Box 23, Folder 324-326)
      - Freight Trends and Policies and Some Implications for Metropolitan Regions, Conference on Urban Transportation at Syracuse University, Syracuse, New York; with accompanying research, March 29, 1971; 20 items. (Box 23, Folder 327-328)
      - Some Continental Transport Problems Facing the Pacific Northwest, General Conference of the Pacific Northwest Trade Association, Seattle, Washington; with accompanying research, October 31, 1955; 50 items. (Box 23, Folder 329-332)
    - Publications and Research:
      - Control of Entry into Surface Transport Under the Interstate Commerce Act, U.S. Government Sponsored Study. Manuscript and research, 1959; 500 (Box 23, Folder 333-337)
      - A Critique of Governmental Intervention in Transport, for proposed anthology: Regional Transportation Planning: Problems and Prospects, 1971; 3 items. (Box 24, Folder 338)
      - General Economics of Transport Publications, 1940-1966; 10 items. (Box 339)
      - Interregional and Intraregional Traffic of the Mountain-Pacific Area in 1939; research material, 1948; 95 items. (Box 340-343)
      - Railroad Transportation and National Policy, Brookings Institute; manuscript, research, and publication material, 1959; 1210 (Box 344-358)
      - Research Basis for Corrective Action with Respect to Inter-territorial Freight Rates, A, Law and Contemporary Problems 12:532-48. Article and Correspondence, Summer 1947; 12 items. (Box 359)
      - Revision of National Transport Regulation Policy, The American Economic Review 45:910-18. Article, galley proofs, and correspondence, December 1955; 20 items. (Box 25, Folder 360)
      - Taxing Washington's Motor Vehicles Equitably for Highway Services. Report submitted to the Joint Fact-Finding Committee on Highways, Streets, and Bridges. Washington State. Publication, galleys, manuscript, research, and correspondence, 1950; 590 (Box 25, Folder 361-394)